Register of the First Aid For Hungary, 1956-1958
Hoover Institution Archives
First Aid For Hungary,
1956-1958
57014
3 manuscript boxes (1.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, contribution lists, clippings, and printed matter, relating to relief and resettlement of Hungarian refugees.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1957.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (3 reels).
Access Point
International relief; Refugees; Hungary; Hungary-History-Revolution, 1956; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964
Historical Note
I was again called into service at the time of the Hungarian uprisings in the last months of 1956. I accepted the honorary chairmanship of an organization called "First Aid for Hungary, Inc.," which had been formed as the result of a meeting of several prominent Americans of Hungarian descent called by Dr. Tibor Eckhardt on October 29, 1956; it was organized to render vital services in a sudden emergency. Our immediate objective was to bring aid to the hundreds of Hungarian Freedom Fighters who had been forced to seek refuge in neighboring Austria and had thus cast an enormous burden upon that country. We were one of only two foreign charities actually operating at the Hungarian border during those first frenzied weeks. Immediate aid was rendered through seventeen first-aid stations, four field kitchens,and three mobile pharmacies set up in the border zone to distribute clothing and medical supplies. We were also able to send food and medical supplies into Hungary itself -at first by direct shipment, then through the International Red Cross, and finally by direct shipment again. During the latter part of this organization's life, as Russian tanks halted the flow of Hungarians across the border, we turned our attention to aiding the refugees in camps in Austria and for several months provided a number of them with supplies, especially for children, and also with care for the sick, wounded, and maternity cases. In February 1957, we determined upon a specific program to deal with the emergency created by the interruptions of studies, particulary of high-school age children. We supported programs in Austria, Belgium, Germany, and United States by providing funds and textbooks. Later, our efforts were extended to the problem of higher education for refugee students. Aid to the education of these young people took some of our work out of the temporary and gave it an added significance of future and permanent value. My personal feelings on the matter were conveyed in a message of mine which was read at the Protest Meeting for the Hungarians in Madison Square Garden on November 8, 1956:
Every people striving for freedom has over our whole national life appealed to the American heart. But seldom in these hundred and sixty years has any people shown such magnificent courage and sacrifice as we have seen in these past few weeks in Hungary. Whatever we can do to alleviate their suffering and to protest this wickedness must lie on the American conscience.
Among the officers of the organization, in addition to myself as Honorary Chairman, were Dr. Tibor Eckhardt, President, and Mr. Tibor Jahoda, Treasurer. Through October 31, 1957, the funds raised amounted to $1,143,055.43.
(from Herbert Hoover, An American Epic, Volume IV)
Series Description
- Office Files, 1956-1958. (Boxes 1-2)
  Correspondence, fact sheet, lists, press releases, publicity material, clippings, and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Individuals' Files, 1956-1957. (Boxes 2-3)
  Correspondence, list, reports, statements, and clipping, arranged alphabetically by name of member or other individual working on behalf of the organization
- Subject File, 1947-1957. (Box 3)
  Letter, reports, statistics, and printed matter, relating mainly to Hungary and in particular the revolt of 1956, arranged alphabetically by subject
Container List
- Office File, 1956-1958
  - Contributions file
    - Letters
      - General (Box 1., Folder 1)
      - Thank you letters, arranged alphabetically by name of donor
        - A-K (Folder 2)
        - L-Y (Folder 3)
    - Lists
      - General
        - 1956 December
          - 10-15 (Folder 4)
          - 15-24 (Folder 5)
          - 24-28 (Box 2., Folder 1)
        - 1956 December 29-1957 February 21 (Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1956 November 6-1957 March 1 (Folder 4)
      - 1957 February 25-1958 March 15 (Folder 5)
    - American Red Cross (Folder 6)
    - International Rescue Committee (Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 8)
  - Fact sheet (Folder 9)
  - Press releases. Includes press release announcing dissolution of the organization, 1957 March 5 (Folder 10)
  - Publicity material
    - General (Folder 11)
    - Clippings (Folder 12)
  - Report. "Report on First Aid for Hungary, 1956-1958" (Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 14)
- Individuals' Files, 1956-1957
  - Eckhardt, Tibor (President)
    - Correspondence
      - Galpin, Perrin (Box 2., Folder 15)
      - Hoover, Herbert (Folder 16)
    - Report. "Organization and First Month Activities," 1956 December 7 (Folder 17)
  - Galpin, Perrin
    - Correspondence
      - Alverson, Gabriele (Folder 18)
      - Beal, Gerald (Folder 19)
      - Belen, Jaques (Folder 20)
      - Bondy, Heinz (Folder 21)
      - Hartigan, John (Folder 22)
      - Hoover, Herbert (Folder 23)
      - Hughes, John Chambers (Box 3., Folder 1)
      - Leach, Charles N. (Folder 2)
      - Tuck, Hallam W. (Folder 3)
      - Vegh, Jeno (Folder 4)
    - Report on trip to Vienna, 1957 January (Folder 5)
  - Hoover, Herbert (Honorary Chairman)
    - Correspondence
      - Eisenhower, Dwight. Includes correspondence with Richard Nixon (Folder 6)
      - Hoover, Herbert, Jr. (Folder 7)
    - Statements (Folder 8)
  - Hoover, Herbert, Jr. Clipping (Folder 9)
  - Shouse, Jouett (Chairman of Washington Branch)
    - Correspondence
      - Adams, Phelps D. (Folder 10)
      - Bruguiere, Margaret L. (Folder 11)
      - Eckhardt, Tibor (Folder 12)
      - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Folder 13)
      - Galpin, Perrin (Folder 14)
      - Hoover, Herbert (Folder 15)
      - Japan. Ambassador to the United States (Folder 16)
      - Troxler, Paul D. (Folder 17)
    - List of companies contacted for contributions (Folder 18)
    - Thank you letters for contributions (Folder 19)
  - Tuck, Hallam. Correspondence
    - Galpin, Perrin (Folder 20)
    - Hoover, Herbert (Folder 21)
  - Voorhees, Tracy S.
    - Correspondence
      - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Folder 22)
      - French, Paul C. (Folder 23)
      - Galpin, Perrin (Folder 24)
      - Hoover, Herbert (Folder 25)
      - Tuck, Hallam (Folder 26)
    - Reports. See also Correspondence/Hoover, Herbert (Folder 27)
- Subject File, 1947-1957
  - Freedom Fighters of Hungary. Printed matter (Box 3., Folder 28)
  - Hungary - History - Revolution, 1956
    - The Revolt in Hungary: A Documantary Chronology of Events, 1956 October 23 - November 4. Printed copy (Folder 29)
    - A Magyar forradalom es szabadsagharc, 1956 October 23 - November 9. Printed copy issued by Free Europe Press (in Hungarian) (Folder 30)
  - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions. Printed matter (Folder 31)
  - President's Committee for Hungarian Refugee Relief. See INDIVIDUALS' FILES/Voorhees, Tracy S. (chairman)
  - Radio Free Europe. Typescript letter of Willis D. Crittenberger (Free Europe Committee) to Eugene Holman (Crusade for Freedom), 1956 December 3 (Folder 32)
  - Refugees - Hungary. Reports
    - General (Folder 33)
    - Austria (Folder 34)
    - United States. Includes statistics (Folder 35)
  - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration. Printed matter (Folder 36)